Guide to the Lauren Henkin Photographs, 2015 May RL.11526
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lauren Henkin photographs
2015 May
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Henkin, Lauren, 1974-
RL.11526
1.5 Linear Feet 1 box; 47 items
The forty color inkjet photographs in this collection were taken by Lauren Henkin in May 2015 in and around Hale County, Alabama, part of the Alabama and Mississippi "Black Belt." The prints (17x22 inches) form part of a body of work titled "What's Lost is Found." Subjects include rural inhabitants, white and black; residences of all kinds, including many interiors; church exteriors and interiors; and rural and wooded landscapes, As part of the photographer's intent to capture the spirituality she perceived in the place and its people, captions for each image are taken from biblical verses. Collection includes five sheets with detailed captions and locations for each image. The Black Belt region is noted for its black topsoil, cotton plantations, the legacy of slavery, civil rights history, and photographic history: Walker Evans, Gordon Parks, and William Christenberry both produced some of their most well-known work in these same places. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
40 photographic prints; 7 supplemental sheets
Biographical / Historical
Born in Washington, D.C., artist Lauren Henkin graduated with a Bachelor of Arts in Architecture from Washington University in St. Louis and now resides in Maine.
Henkin's work is focused on the tension between preservation and extinction — from fading relationships to invasive growths to material possessions — as told in the American vernacular.
Her work resides in over twenty institutional collections including the Cleveland Museum of Art, Portland Art Museum, Yale University, Smith College Museum of Art, and Brown University's Bell Gallery, among others. She is also the founder of Vela Noche, a publisher of handmade books and editions.
Henkin received the 2017 Duke University Archive of Documentary Arts Award for Southern Documentarians.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Images may only be used for educational, non-commercial purposes; any other use requires the photographer's permission.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Lauren Henkin photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2017.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The inkjet prints are on Canson Edition Etching Rag paper, and were printed using Epson Ultrachrome K3 Inks.
Content Description
The forty color inkjet photographs in this collection were taken by Lauren Henkin in May 2015 in and around Hale County, Alabama, part of the Alabama and Mississippi "Black Belt." The prints (17x22 inches) form part of a body of work titled "What's Lost is Found." Subjects include rural inhabitants, white and black; house interiors; church exteriors and interiors; and rural and wooded landscapes. Many of the images contain religious symbols and objects such as crosses. As part of the photographer's intent to capture the spirituality she perceived in the place and its people, captions for each image are taken from biblical verses. Collection includes five sheets, also 17x22 inches, with detailed captions and locations for each image.
The Black Belt region is noted for its black topsoil, cotton plantations, the legacy of slavery, civil rights history, and photographic history: Walker Evans, Gordon Parks, and William Christenberry both produced some of their most well-known work in these same places.
From the artist's statement: "It wasn't a place that should be simplified by an imposed narrative. The people I met had a request, 'Please, no more photos of poor kids barefoot on a front porch.' I wanted to show the complexity of a place that could in one moment take the viewer into the woods, to the home of a man that lives with his dogs in the poorest of conditions to the grounds of a mansion covered in soft southern light, to the interior of a home populated with Andrew Wyeth reproductions depicting wind and billowing curtains. I wanted to avoid stereotypical perspectives on the racial and socioeconomic divides, and instead, focus on the interconnectedness between the landscape, the flesh, and the spiritual."
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
African Americans -- Alabama -- Portraits; Country life -- Alabama; Documentary photography -- Alabama; People -- Alabama -- Photographs; Spirituality in art; Alabama -- Photographs; Alabama -- Religious life and customs; Alabama -- Social conditions; Black Belt (Ala. and Miss.) -- Photographs; Black Belt (Ala. and Miss.) -- Social conditions; Hale County (Ala.) -- Photographs; Southern States -- Social conditions -- 21st century; Southern States -- Social life and customs -- 21st century; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
- What's Lost is Found, 2015 May; 40 prints 1 box
  - Summary panels with image thumbnails and captions; two title sheets, 2017 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Five paper sheets measuring 17x22 inches, each with eight color thumbnail images of each photograph, accompanied by detailed contextual captions and image locations. Also includes two title pages, also 17x22 inches.
  - "The life of the flesh is in the blood", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0001)
  - "In all your ways acknowledge Him, And He will make your paths straight", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0002)
  - "After a fire a sound of gentle blowing", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0003)
  - "The lifting up of my hands as the evening offering", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0004)
  - "By wisdom a house is built, and by understanding it is established; by knowledge the rooms are filled with all precious and pleasant riches", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0005)
  - "Whoever comes to me shall not hunger, and whoever believes in me shall never thirst", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0006)
  - "Flesh gives birth to flesh, but the Spirit gives birth to spirit", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0007)
  - "Whoever comes to me will never go hungry, and whoever believes in me will never be thirsty", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0008)
  - "For where two or three gather in my name, there am I with them", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0009)
  - "Go in peace. The journey on which you go is under the eye of the Lord", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0010)
  - "For the poor will never cease to be in the land", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0011)
  - "A rich man's wealth is his strong city, And like a high wall in his own imagination", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0012)
  - "Look to the lord and his strength", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0013)
  - "She is a tree of life to those who take hold of her", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0014)
  - "So you will walk in the way of good men and keep to the paths of the righteous", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0015)
  - "Come, let us sing for joy to the LORD; let us shout aloud to the Rock of our salvation", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0016)
  - "The tree of life", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0017)
  - "As a deer pants for flowing streams, so pants my soul for you, O God", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0018)
  - "One who has unreliable friends soon comes to ruin, but there is a friend who sticks closer than a brother", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0019)
  - "So then let us cast off the works of darkness and put on the armor of light", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0020)
  - "Let us make man in our image, after our likeness", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0021)
  - "And he is before all things, and in him all things hold together", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0022)
  - "But all things should be done decently and in order", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0023)
  - "So, if your eye is healthy, your whole body will be full of light", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0024)
  - "Love your neighbor as yourself", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0025)
  - "Of old you laid the foundation of the earth, and the heavens are the work of your hands", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0026)
  - "Out of his heart will flow rivers of living water", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0027)
  - "We have all become like one who is unclean, and all our righteous deeds are like a polluted garment", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0028)
  - "He has made everything beautiful in its time", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0029)
  - "Now the Lord is the Spirit, and where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is freedom", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0030)
  - "The light shines in the darkness, and the darkness has not overcome it", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0031)
  - "When the righteous cry for help, the Lord hears and delivers them out of all their troubles", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0032)
  - "Keep this book of the law always on your lips", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0033)
  - "Your kingdom come, your will be done, on earth as it is in heaven", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0034)
  - "By man his blood shall be shed", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0035)
  - "He restores my soul. He leads me in paths of righteousness for his name's sake", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0036)
  - "The name of the LORD is a fortified tower; the righteous run to it and are safe", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0037)
  - "A friend loves at all times, and a brother is born for a time of adversity", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0038)
  - "Call to me and I will answer you, and will tell you great and hidden things that you have not known", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0039)
  - "Forsaken among the dead", 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11526-P-0040)